[Music]
hi my name is claudo I'm a soft engineer
working on business Central here in
copen and today I'm joined by my
colleague chthon hi my name is Chan
toaya I'm also a soft trade engineer
working business Central in Copenhagen
in this session we are going to be
talking about the new capabilities that
we are bringing to the business Central
mobile app and mainly we are going to be
talking about some new additions that we
brought to you via the control addin API
some new warehousing scenarios and
lastly we are going to be showing some
Demos in the previous release we have
brought to you some new features on the
business Central mobile app namely we
brought to you the barcod scanning
functionality tell me and searching data
and we also mentioned that we were
working on bringing support for work
worksheet pages on phone and we did so
in this
release the worksheet pages on mobile
phones are a simplified version of what
we already have for desktop and tablet
they are simplified meaning that there's
a shorter header section of course you
also have all the worksheet lines on the
same page that you're used to and a full
summary section and uh to edit the data
one would have to Simply tap on the
desired area of the line it's really
important to mention that we haven't
done any changes to the desktop and
tablet worksheet pages and this
functionality will work out of the box
if you have already been implemented uh
already um the worksheet pages in
business Central however we are um
advising you to check how they look like
and make sure that uh uh you have the
desired user interface
in the last release we brought to you
native barcode scanning capability so we
developed the Integrations with both the
camera uh barcode scanning capability
but also with laser scanning devices
nevertheless unfortunately due to some
uh technical limitations we were not
able to make these available on SAS but
we did listen to your feedback as
partners and we did so in this
release in terms of of the supported
barcode types The Matrix Remains the
Same as you can see on the right side
side pane you can see all the barcode
types that we support for the camera
barcod scanning and then when it comes
to the laser one of course it's bound to
the device that you are
using and now let's go through a summary
of the mobile app capabilities for
barcode scanning in the first scenario
probably as you already know um we offer
a UI button that indicates barcode
scanning functionality
in the second scenario it is based on
the same native functionality as the
first scenario however we intend to
provide a developers with a more
customiz customizable experience and
therefore we are bringing this
capability in Al where developers can
uptake it and do uh some certain
implementations based on the context on
it and then the third scenario um this
is something that we specifically
tailored for laser barcode scanners
these are used for example for warehouse
workers who are using the app to scan
multiple products scenario number one
consists of um adding a UI button that
acts as an action to trigger the camera
barcode scanning functionality is is it
is really easy to addit to a page or an
exist or a new La page all you have to
do is to annotate a field of type code
and text with the property extended data
type equals barcode once you've done so
this will instruct the mobile client to
show the barcode scanning button when
the page is rendered on a supported
device the second scenario represents uh
the same native capability for barcode
scanning and that is using the camera uh
Barcode Scanner um but we allow a
developers to build a more customizable
experience for example it can be started
from a roll center queue an action a
button a link or some automated logic
when a page is open for example
and once a barcod barcodes it scanned
then it just Returns the value to Al for
for further code processing in the
previous release we were not able to
make this capability available on SAS
due to some technical limitations
however in this release we are bringing
you a new alapi based on controll D that
is supposed to replace the donet based
API and therefore making this feature
available on SAS and now let's see um an
example of this API also you if you want
to see how that looks like you can just
scan the QR code but let's look at how
it looks like we've added the new API to
our open source GitHub repo namely BC
apps and you can find it under the
control addin name camera Barcode
Scanner provider addin the addin has uh
multiple procedures and multiple events
the procedures are meant to interact
with the camera barod scanning
capability
via the request bar code request bar
code async and then the events are the
following when uh when there's a
successful barcode scanning event the
barcode available event will be called
uh and will take two arguments the
barcode and the format of the barcode
and in case of a failure of course the
event barcode failure will be called uh
lastly when mounting this controller in
on a page when rendering it on a page
the controller in ready with the flag is
supported with be called denoting
whether or not the capability is
available on the users mobile now let's
see a demo with this new capability Chan
thanks laio uh for the demo today I'll
be using a data logic memo 10 Android
device which is a native uh uh Barcode
Scanner which can do both uh camera
barcode scanning and also laser one on
this device have um uh installed
business mobile app which I'm going to
use for the
demo so as clao mentioned uh with the
scenario 2 uh it's about camera barcode
scanning to Showcase that one I'm going
to open um item journal and then try to
do a positive adjustment of some of our
items in that process I'm going to uh
enter item tracking lines so let's get
to the mobile app now so on the mobile
app um you can see that I have tagged
item Journal already in this release we
also uh worked on um you know improving
the brick layouts for all of our um uh
you know worksheet Pages as Claudia
mentioned earlier now that we support uh
worksheet pages on mobile devices it was
time for us to make the brick layout uh
and make it make the user experience
more appealing so this how the um the
user sorry item Journal looks like and
you can see on the bottom right corner
there show details if you press that one
you can see see the fact boxes that are
on the item journal page so let's get
back to the item
Journal so here uh we have two lines so
one is U we are you know positively
adjusting uh s semi-automatic uh coffee
machine which is a Serial tracked item
and the next line is a hold roasted
beans from Indonesia and it's a lot
tracked item so in both the cases we are
trying to positively adjust it by five
quantity so so because these are item
tracked so we need to fill in the item
tracking lines before proceeding with
this item Journal so let's uh get and
set the item tracking lines to set the
item tracking lines I have selected the
first line and we have action called
item tracking
lines clicking that opens U the item
tracking lines page so this is the page
where we have enabled the uh the camera
Barcode Scanner capability when there's
action called scan multiple
invoking that one camera starts U
actively looking for barcodes so in this
uh on this line if you remember it is um
it is a serially track serial track item
so we'll start by scanning this serial
numbers so I'll click on scan multiple
and uh obviously it will ask if we are
going to scan serial number Lot number
package number in this case is
serial so once we do that one the camera
starts looking for U the bar codes that
was one you can see that the camera
after processing the first one it moves
on to the second
one and that was
um so item quantity is five here so
let's scan five
items four
and the last one
being all right now you saw that U all
five five coffee machines were scanned
in and at the at the end when uh it has
fulfilled all the item uh tracking
requirements then we show this message
saying that the item tracking is defined
and we can move on to the next
line so next line will be our whole
roasted U be from Indonesia so here
again we are going to go to item
tracking
line so here um because this is a lot
track item we going to scan some U lot
numbers so scan multiple again and this
time we are going to select Lot
number so this uh let's look at the QR
code so that was
one and you can see that uh the quantity
is getting incremented for the same Lot
number all right so even this uh line is
fulfilled so now uh the user can go
ahead with this item journal and process
this one first further so this was uh
the demo for the scenario 2 that Claudio
uh just explained and uh you know if you
want to enable this uh kind of
capability that is uh the cameras uh
Barcode Scanner capability in your app
and on your page let's look at how the
code would look like so uh what I'll do
is uh first I'll take you through how
the code used to be in the previous
release and then I will show you how uh
we have changed the code in this release
uh by using the control uh addins so the
code you're looking is uh this is how it
would look if you wanted the camera
Barcode Scanner capability you would uh
first Define uh the net object called
camera Barcode Scanner provider so once
you have um you know declared this
variable the next thing is to uh you
know see if uh in the runtime to see if
uh the camera scanning capabili is
available on this uh device so that you
can do by calling the EAS available
uh function on the camera barcode do
scan provider object which becomes your
step two in a way and uh once you find
that it is supported then you go ahead
and uh uh create an instance of the
object which will be three once you have
done um you know step three then you
need to U you know to actively look for
uh the barcode scanner you need to
activate the camera by calling uh the
request barcode BAS sync just uh like we
are doing this uh like this in the in
the
example so once you do this the camera
opens on the the device and starts
looking for the barcodes and once you
gets a successful hit then it will uh
come to the trigger called Barcode
Scanner provider barcode
available yeah here you get the barcode
that was read and also the format and
your step five is to process this one so
this are um you know this how the code
was in the previous release if you
wanted this capability and moving from
previous release to this release we
moved away from net to to uh using the
control addin in the current release uh
this how the code would look like uh to
add this capability on your page you
would uh first start by adding uh the
control add in on your page so uh here
you can see we have added the control
adding the camera Barcode Scanner
provider adding on the on this
page and once you add this one the next
step for you is to uh find out if uh the
camera Barcode Scanner is available on
this environment or on the device so
that you can do um inside the control
adding ready so these where uh the es
supported argument brings in that
information if uh the barcode scanner is
available or not depending on that that
one you take the next step so here um if
it's available
the the next thing is to actually
activate the camera to um start scanning
which you're you know in like in the
previous case we going to do in the
action by calling request barcode async
on the control addin which will be your
step three so once you do this one as H
with the as with the net variable the
camera start scanning uh for any
barcodes once it gets hit it uh calls
the barcode available U trigger
and the barcode comes in and this is
where you handle the barcode or process
the barcode and in U like item tracking
lines if you want to have U The
Continuous scanning kind of U uh
experience then uh you basically call
the request barcode async again after
processing U the barcode you already got
so this how you get uh The Continuous
scanning kind of U experience so these
are What U uh looks the scenario two
looks uh in code back to Claudia thank
you ch
now let's talk about scen number three
in this scenario we are going to be
focusing on integration with dedicated
barcode scanners uh that are mainly
mainly used by people in warehouses and
it's important to mention that in order
to update this functionality it requires
configurations at two levels first level
would be a configuration at the device
level so in order to have this
capability available in the BC app one
would actually need to configure the
laser bcode Scanner with the BC
application uh and we also have a
documentation for you about how to do
that and also it's really important to
mention that this capability is
available only on Android OS devices
then the second level of uh
configuration that uh an Al developer
would have to do is to uh implement the
scanning capability in Al um and in
order to do so you would have to
explicitly start listening for incoming
bar codes on an page and then you have
to do that only once and as the user
keeps on scanning then uh barcode
barcode data would be will be sent to
that page of course one can actually
register multiple barcode scanning
events on multiple Pages however it
would always be sent the data would be
always sent to the topmost
page similar as in the previous scenario
we were not able to make the capability
available in the last release on SAS but
with the addition of the new alapi based
on the control D which are meant to
replace the net based apis we are also
bringing you this capability on SS and
let's take a look how the API looks like
you can already see that this API looks
similar to the previous apis that we saw
except that this is meant only for
integration with the laser dedicated
barcode scanning device it consists of
two procedures which are meant to
request or register a page to start
listening to incoming barcode scanning
events and then once uh a barcode is
scanned the event barcode received will
be called and we'll have the subsequent
data uh meaning the barcode data and the
type of the format similar as in the
previous uh controll in this this
controlled in also has an event
controlled in ready which denotes
whether or not the users uh device is
supporting this capability and now let's
see a demo with this scenario Chan uh
for this demo um U you know as the as
the scenario three which is the barcode
scanner the laser based Barcode Scanner
is the mainly aimed at U the warehouse
workers the scenario I'm going to show
now is also U uh you know warehouse
worker related so uh you can on the
screen you can see um um a ni and pick
which is on U warehouse worker um role
Center so when I open that one you can
see there is a pig document in in this
release what we have done is also add uh
gestures to many of the warehouse
related U lists so that it's easier for
warehouse worker to use the gesture do
different actions that are relevant for
those uh list pages so in this uh page
you can see we have um gesture you know
which is a right swipe to assign the pig
document uh to yourself so once once I
do that one it appears in U my pick um
list and now I can work on this so when
I uh open this one this is what you see
so for people uh who don't know what
Warehouse pick is it is a document with
a set of instruction for the warehouse
worker uh to move items from uh one bin
in a location to another bin so for
example if you're in the manufacturing
you might want the components that use
for manufacturing in the consumption bin
so the warehouse pick might be to move
uh the components from uh your storage
bin to your consumption bin and if
you're selling an item then moving the
item from uh from a storage bin to uh
shipment bin might be covered in the
warehouse pick so this uh pick that we
have created looks like this it is
sorted by action type which means all
the uh the Tes and are together and all
the place so that the warehouse worker
can go to the storage and handle all the
take lines so that U things are put on
the trolley and take it to the
destination and do the place operation
so let's uh go ahead and do the take
operation now yeah this is how the
warehouse pick document U looks like so
it has uh you know three take lines and
three Place lines so basically you're
moving U the items from one bin on in
the location to another bin so if you
look at uh the T the first take Line
This is for taking the item S100 which
is a semi-automatic U coffee machine and
uh it should be moved from U you know
bin
w1001 so and U we have action called
scan executing which it opens the line
details so this is the page we are built
uh to show only the relevant information
for the warehouse worker so the first
section shows you the line information
basically it's a action type take and
what you should take and from which bin
and the second part is what you're going
to enter now so this is the serial track
item so let's go ahead and uh scan a
serial number which I have it here
so you could uh see that U it was quite
fast and the quantity to handle is set
to one and the serial number is also set
so when we scan and set information
about serial or lot or package on on the
take line we also transferred that on to
the place line to make it easier for the
warehouse worker so once um you know
this is done this uh because out
standing quantity is same as quantity to
handle this line is fulfilled so let's
move to the next line so here again it's
another line for the same item so let's
go ahead and
scan again so the serial number is
filled earlier I mentioned that we show
only the relevant information so here
you can see because it's a Serial track
item we show the serial number for a lot
tracked item we show the lot number and
likewise for a package number for
package tracked items so now that uh we
have scanned two of this coffee machine
the next one is the roasted beans which
is lot track let's go and uh you know
scan some uh lot
numbers yep I did uh five scans you can
see that it was quite fast and uh
quantity to handle has been set to five
and the lot number has been set now the
vas worker can take these items to the
the destination bins and do the similar
activity on the place lines and then
he's uh or he or she is able to uh
register the weos pick so this was the
demo right and um if you want to have
this kind of capability in your app then
let's see how the code would look like
so like in the previous case I'll start
by showing how uh the code looked in the
previous release and then I'll move on
to the how the code looks uh now so in
the previous relase again even this
capability was exposed through a net
object so you would uh you would uh you
know Define or declare this variable
barcode scanner on your page which will
give you this capability and once you uh
add that one the next step would be to
see if it's uh the barcode scanner is
available or not that you do it by use
available function on the on the net
object and once you you know find that
it is available then you create which
will be your step three and then request
Barcode Scanner async will be called
which U again puts the the scanner into
the listening mode to listen to any
incoming U incoming barcodes so you can
see that uh this is once you do the
request Barcode Scanner async it's
already in The Continuous scanning mode
you don't have to uh call these things
again so whenever there is a successful
um uh barcode rate it comes to the
barcode received um barcode received
trigger and this is where uh you you uh
you know handle or you process the
barcode and which will be your stepy so
this is how it Wass and uh let's see how
the code looks in this
release again even in this case uh we
moved away from the net comp to the
control adding as a step one you need to
Define your or add the control adding
onto the page in the user control uh
section which will be your step one and
uh the way you find out if uh the
barcode scanner is available on the
device or not is by you know looking at
the is supported uh argument that comes
in uh once you know that it is supported
then you go uh go ahead and call the
request Barcode Scanner a sync which
again you know starts the barcode
scanner in you know in the listening
mode and it's listening for any barcode
U that that is scanned from the device
and you now once the barcode is read it
comes to the barcode received U trigger
and that's where you uh that's where you
process the barcodes so uh and uh once
you add the control add in and start
listening the the listening part uh is
uh uh you know it's actively listening
until you uh the page is closed and yeah
this is what I wanted to show as part of
this one back to uh Cloud
you thank you Chan for the amazing demos
uh now let's talk a bit more about the
new controllin API the new controlin API
is based on the existing controll Adin
that has have been available in Al for a
while now but these controll Adin are
special in the sense that they are only
uh and can be only used to interact with
client extens ility methods such as
barcode scanning functionality from a
security perspective it is really
important to mention that they are a
close system meaning that uh they can
only interact with uh the barcode
scanning functionality or any other
client extensibility methods and it's
only us Microsoft who can provide this
type of addings and you as partners can
update the functionality and build your
experiences uh based on them from a UI
perspective they are UI less meaning
that there's no if frame associated with
these control edins as you might be
already used with your current control
edins and therefore since there's no
iframe styling properties are also not
applied we also know that control edins
are usually used to do some computation
via JavaScript however these type of
control edins do not support that at
all
going through the next slide um it's
really important to mention that the net
based apis are still supported meaning
that if you already have uptaken any
barcode scanning functionality in your
application these are still going to be
uh supported however uh we plan to
migrate all the that net based apis to
control Adin and therefore we strongly
encourage to update any new barcode
scanning functionality in your app using
the controllin API and in the upcoming
releases we are also going to be making
other client and Sensibility methods
such as the location provider to be
available via the control
addins in terms of the resources for the
mobile app here I have three links that
you can use to either see some code
samples some documentation or to even
download the BC mobile app and start
using or implementing these capabilities
that we just talked about in this
presentation furthermore we are always
looking forward to receive your feedback
and therefore reach to us on any social
media platform that we are using for
example Twitter or if you have some
ideas around these capabilities that we
presented in this uh presentation please
do some meet them on BC ideas thank you
for watching the presentation uh about
the business center mobile app and we
are looking forward to see what you're
going to be building with these new
capabilities this is it thank
you